A Register to the Nataliia Apollinarievna Logunova Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Nataliia Logunova papers
1930-1978.
2008C46
Logunova, Nataliia, d. 1972?
8 microfilm reels (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diary, correspondence, fictional and other writings, and photographs, relating to Russian literature and Russian émigré affairs.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
The collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Originals
In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Biographical Chronology
1903 February 26 Born, Odessa, Russia
1920 Fled to Romania
1944 Deported to German camps, later lived in Displaced persons camps
1952 Arrived in the United States of America
1962 Author, Irina
1968 Author, Olenka Bell
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers contain the correspondence and writings of Nataliia Logunova, a Russian journalist and writer, who emigrated to the United States, and also used the pen-names Nataliia Snarskaia, Nikolai Tallin, and NETLI. Logunova's Correspondence includes letters to publishers and writers. Among her Speeches and Writings are two published novels, Irina and Olen'ka Bell, as well as numerous articles, unpublished novels, plays, and short stories. A recurring theme in her writings is the fate of Russian émigrés, particular in the Displaced Persons camps. Of particular interest is her unpublished memoir "Tri epokhi."
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the online catalog.
Subjects
Russian literature.; Russians--United States.
Container List
- Diaries, 1970-1972. (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Holograph
- Correspondence, 1949-1972 and undated.
  Address lists, cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General, undated
    - Addresses
      - General, undated. (Folder 1: 2)
        Holograph (undated). Includes list of bookstores and radio stations
      - Publishers, undated. (Folder 1: 3)
        Holograph (notebook). Includes list of documents sent to the Bakhmeteff archives at Columbia University, and recipients of Logunova's novel Irina in 1963
    - Letters, 1969-1972 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
    - Postcards, 1950-1972 and undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Unidentified, 1949-1972 and undated (Folder 1: 6)
  - Brunner, Robert Mikhailovich, 1956-1971 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Delianich, Ariadna Ivanovna, 1972 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Evets, Arkadii Ivanovich, 1972 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Foster, Ludmila Aleksandrovna, 1972 and undated (Folder 1: 10)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra, 1970 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Harkins, William, 1970 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Iiulianiia, Abbess, 1972 and undated (Folder 1: 13)
  - International Pen Club, 1969-1971 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Iur'eva, Zoia Osipovna, 1970 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Koenig, Liubov', undated (Folder 1: 16)
  - Koriakov, Mikhail Mikhailovich, undated (Folder 1: 17)
  - Langer, Georg, 1967 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Lukashkin, Anatolii Stefanovich, 1972 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Magerovskii, Lev Florianovich, 1961-1972 and undated. (Folder 1: 20)
    Includes several lists of materials forwarded to the Bakhmeteff Archive of Columbia University
  - Maksimova-Vertepova, Tamara Borisovna, 1972 and undated (Folder 1: 21)
  - Mart'ianov, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1972 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Mort, Viktor Konstantinovich, undated (Folder 1: 23)
  - Mosley, Philip E., 1961 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Museum of Russian Culture, 1969 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Perov, Pavel Nikolaevich, 1972 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Petrov, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1972 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Pozdniakov, Vladimir Vasilievich, 1972 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Pronin, A., 1970 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Savin, Valerian Luk'ianovich, 1971-1972 and undated (Folder 1: 30)
  - Sokolov, Vladimir Dimitrievich, 1972 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Tanchik, Elizaveta, 1972 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Taranenko, Grigorii Daniilovich, 1972 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Tsertitskii, Gleb and Mariia, 1964-1969 and undated (Folder 1: 34)
  - Veinbaum, Mark Efimovich, 1958-1972 (Folder 1: 35)
- Speeches and Writings, 1943-1978.
  Articles, drafts, notebooks, notes, and monographs, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - General
      - Undated. (Folder 1: 36)
        Typescripts
      - 1951-1971. (Box-folder 2: 1)
        Holographs and typescripts
    - Articles
      - General
        - General, 1955-1962. (Folder 2: 2)
        - English publications, 1959 and undated. (Folder 2: 3)
          Typescripts. Includes related correspondence and an outline for a scenario
        - Russian – literary subjects
          - General, 1949-1969 and undated. (Folder 2: 4)
          - Gogol, Nikolai, 1949-1952. (Folder 2: 5)
            Holographs
          - Pasternak, Boris, 1965-1969 and undated. (Folder 2: 6)
            Holograph and typescripts
          - Paustovskii, Konstantin, 1968-1978. (Folder 2: 7)
          - Pushkin, Aleksandr, 1947-1949 and undated. (Folder 2: 8)
          - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr, 1963-1969. (Folder 2: 9)
      - Nashi vesti, 1957-1959. (Folder 2: 10)
      - Novoe russkoe slovo, 1949-1972 and undated.
        Typescripts.
        - 1949-1959 and undated (Folder 2: 11)
        - 1960-1972 (Folder 2: 12)
      - Russkaia mysl', 1959-1964 and undated. (Folder 2: 13)
        Includes listing of Logunova's publications in Russkaia mysl'. Holograph and typescripts
      - Russkaia zhizn', 1956-1961 and undated. (Box-folder 3: 1)
      - Soglasie, 1953-1958. (Folder 3: 2)
    - Notebooks, 1944-1951 and undated. (Folder 3: 3)
      Holographs. Includes plays, notes and short stories
    - Notes, 1946-1957 and undated. (Folder 3: 4)
    - Poetry, 1954-1967 and undated. (Folder 3: 5)
  - "Bab'e leto (Indeiskoe leto),", undated. (Folder 3: 6)
    Typescript
  - "Bespravnye,", undated. (Folder 3: 7)
  - "Bol'sheviki prishli,", undated. (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Chekisty v riase,", undated. (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Chernyi,", undated. (Folder 3: 10)
    Holograph and typescripts. Includes English versions entitled "Blacky"
  - "Deti na stsene,", undated. (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Diadi Soso,", undated. (Folder 3: 12)
  - "Dva snovideniia,", undated. (Folder 3: 13)
  - "General Meleter i ego sem'ia,", undated. (Folder 3: 14)
  - "Gvozd' v kresle," (Play), undated. (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Iz rodnogo goroda,", undated. (Folder 3: 16)
  - "Kommunizm bez prikras,", undated. (Folder 3: 17)
  - "Odessa," undated collection of essays. (Folder 3: 18)
    Typescript. Includes handwritten notes
  - "Okhotnich'i rasskazy,", undated. (Box-folder 4: 1)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Po amerikanskim zhurnalam,", undated. (Folder 4: 2)
  - "Posle tretei mirovoi,", undated. (Folder 4: 3)
    Typescript of movie script
  - "Pered litsem vechnosti,", undated. (Folder 4: 4)
  - "Pervyi opyt (iz okhotnicheskikh rasskazov," and other short stories, undated. (Folder 4: 5)
  - "Pesni zakliuchennykh,", undated. (Folder 4: 6)
  - "Reka poshla,", undated. (Folder 4: 7)
  - Sbornik rasskazov, undated. (Folder 4: 8)
    Printed copy of short stories dated 1943-1949. This publication is published under N. Logunova's pen name "Nikolai Tallin"
  - "Sevastopol'tsy,", undated. (Folder 4: 9)
  - "Svoboda dukha i odinochestvo,", undated. (Folder 4: 10)
    Typescript with handwritten corrections
  - "Urodets,", undated. (Folder 4: 11)
  - "V Moskve,", undated. (Folder 4: 12)
  - "Vstrecha s NKVDistami,", undated. (Folder 4: 13)
  - "Kogda skuchaet Amur,", 1944. (Folder 4: 14)
    Holograph, typescript
  - "Proidennyi etap (dnevniki byvsh. DP),", 1945-1952. (Folder 4: 15)
  - "Vyzdorovlenie,", 1946. (Folder 4: 16)
  - "Samyi luchshii," (Play), 1949. (Folder 4: 17)
    Holograph, typescripts
  - "Bez rodiny," (Play), 1950. (Folder 4: 18)
    Holograph, 7 notebooks
  - Children's plays, 1951 and undated. (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Printed copy and typescript
  - "V amerikanskoi sem'e,", 1953. (Folder 5: 2)
  - "Krolikovodstvo v SSSR,", 1954. (Folder 5: 3)
  - "Khorosha strana moia rodnaia,", 1959. (Folder 5: 4)
  - "Chelovek bez litsa,", 1958. (Folder 5: 5)
    Holograph and typescripts. Includes several outlines of an English version entitled "Man Without a Face"
  - "Kvartira,", 1959. (Folder 5: 6)
  - "Nebesnye verbliuzhata,", 1960. (Folder 5: 7)
  - "Zhizn' nachinaetsia snachala,", 1960. (Folder 5: 8)
    Typescript, several versions of the author's movie script based on the novel "Pered litsem vechnosti"
  - "Chetyre vremeni goda,", 1961. (Folder 5: 9)
  - "Rasskazy i povesti,", 1961. (Folder 5: 10)
  - Irina, 1962. (Folder 5: 11)
    Printed copy
  - "Snezhnaia respublika,", 1964. (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - "Otkrovennyi razgovor,", 1965. (Folder 6: 2)
  - "Sovetskii soiuz – Amerika,", 1967. (Folder 6: 3-4)
    Typescript of a collection of memoirs previously published as separate articles in Novoe Russkoe slovo and Russkaia zhizn' between 1949 and 1967
  - Olen'ka Bell, 1968. (Folder 6: 5)
    Printed copy. Includes correspondence and notes relating to the book
  - "Padaiut list'ia,", 1968. (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Tri epokhi,", 1971.
    - Pages 1-226 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Pages 227-452 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Pages 453-755 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Pages 756-992 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Pages 993-1188 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Pages 1189-1358 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - Pages 1359-1435 (Folder 8: 2)
- Printed Matter, 1961. (Folder 8: 3)
  Clippings of articles from Novoe russkoe slovo and Russkaia zhizn'
- Photographs, 1930-1962 and undated.
  325 prints depicting Nataliia Logunova and various persons (mostly unidentified)
  - 1930 and undated. (Folder 8: 4)
    Two prints of unidentified persons
  - 1937. (Folder 8: 5)
    Nikitskii sad in Crimea. Nataliia Logunova with and unidentified group of people, 2 prints
  - 1946-1947. (Folder 8: 6)
    Hameln, Germany. Two prints of Nataliia Logunova with a grouph of unidentified persons. One print includes Bishop Nafanail (L'vov)
  - 1930-1962. (Folder 8: 7)
    Includes photographs of Logunova's stay in displaced persons camps in Germany, as well as after her arrival in the United States. 148 prints
  - 1962. (Folder 8: 8)
    Cape Cod, MA, 19 prints
- Artwork, 1952. (Folder 8: 9)
  Colored oil portrait of Nataliia Logunova